Colette Roberts Artist Interviews
Colette Roberts Artist Interviews
1964-1969
Roberts, Colette, 1910-1971.
37 tapes.
Papers of the American art critic, gallery director.Born in Paris, France, died 1971. Director of Grand Central Moderns (N.Y.), 1952-1968. Collection consists of taped interviews with Will Barnet, Nell Blaine, Victor Candell, Giorgio Cavallon, pianist George Copeland, Ben Cunningham, Fielding Dawson, Marcel Duchamp, Adolph Gottlieb, José Guerrero, Stanley William Hayter, John Hultberg, Jennett Lam, Charlotte Lichtblau, Roy Lichtenstein, Richard Lindner, Robert Mallary, Leo Manso, Ezio Martinelli, Seong Moy, Norman Narotzky, Louise Nevelson, Betty Parsons, Bernard Pfriem, Abraham Rattner, Man Ray, Robert Reid, Ralph Rosenborg, Jason Seley, William Soles, Hyde Solomon, Hedda Sterne, and Reuben Tam.
149545
Biographical History
Colette Jacqueline Roberts (1910-1971) was a French-born artist, teacher, critic and gallery director. Born in Paris, she studied at the École du Louvre, the Academy Ranson, and the Institut d’Art et Archéologie. She moved to the United States during World War II and became a U.S. citizen shortly thereafter, becoming an active part of the New York art world. In addition to her own work, she wrote and lectured on modern art and fostered cultural exchange efforts between her native and adopted countries. As gallery director of the Grand Central Moderns, she gave many unknown artists their first major exposure (among them sculptor Louise Nevelson). In 1960, Roberts received the Palmes Académiques award from the French government for her work as chair of the French section of the American Red Cross, and she was a writer-in-residence at the MacDowell Colony.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Colette Roberts Artist Interviews consists of thirty-seven interviews with notable artists, among them Will Barnet, Victor Candell, Ezio Martinelli, Louise Nevelson, Man Ray, Hedda Sterne and Reuben Tam.
Other Formats Available
All interviews have been digitized. Please contact the repository listed above for more information.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged in alphabetical order. All interviews consists of a single tape unless otherwise noted.
Related Material
has substantial holdings related to art and artists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Art -- Sculptors; Barnet, Will, 1911-2012.; Blaine, Nell, 1922-1996.; Candell, Victor.; Cavallon, Giorgio.; Copeland, George, 1882-1971.; Cunningham, Ben, 1904-1975.; Dawson, Fielding, 1930-2002.; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968.; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974.; Guerrero, José, 1914-1991.; Hayter, Stanley William, 1901-1988.; Hultberg, John.; Lam, Jennett, 1911-; Lichtblau, Charlotte, 1925-; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997.; Lindner, Richard, 1901-1978.; Mallary, Robert, 1917-; Man Ray, 1890-1976.; Manso, Leo, 1914-1993.; Moy, Seong.; Narotzky, Norman, 1928-; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988.; Parsons, Betty.; Rattner, Abraham.; Roberts, Colette, 1910-1971.; Rosenborg, Ralph.; Seley, Jason, 1919-; Solomon, Hyde, 1911-; Sterne, Hedda, 1916-2011.; Tam, Reuben.; Art, American.; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Interviews.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists -- Interviews.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century -- Interviews.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century -- Interviews.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women art critics -- United States.; Audiocassettes.; Interviews.; Sound recordings.; Art critics.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Researcher access to the tapes requires advance notice in order to produce a working copy.
Inventory
- Interviews
  - Abraham Rattner, roberts_c_030; 1/4"reel tape
  - Adolph Gottlieb and John Hultberg, fall 1965; spring 1966; roberts_c_012; 1/4"reel tape
  - Ben Cunningham, March 1966; roberts_c_006; 1/4"reel tape
  - Bernard Pfriem and Jason Seley, fall 1965; roberts_c_029; 1/4"reel tape
  - Betty Parsons Part 1 and 2, 1967; roberts_c_028; 1/4"reel tape
  - Colette Roberts interviews Hedda Sterne, roberts_c_036; 1/4"reel tape
  - Excerpts of Lecture at the Museum of Modern Art on Louise Nevelson and Stanley William Hayten interview in his studio at Rue Boissonade, Paris, roberts_c_014; 1/4"reel tape
  - Ezio Martinelli Part 1, and Seong Moy, spring 1966; fall 1966; roberts_c_025; 1/4"reel tape
  - Ezio Martinelli part 2, spring 1966; roberts_c_024; 1/4"reel tape
  - George Copeland and Louise Nelvelson with N.Y.U., 1966; robers_c_005; 1/4"reel tape
  - Giorgio Cavallon, roberts_c_004; 1/4"reel tape
  - Hyde Solomon, roberts_c_035; 1/4"reel tape
  - Jennett Lam, N.Y.U., spring 1969; roberts_c_016; 1/4"reel tape
  - John Day represented Whitney Museum of Modern Art, etc., spring 1969; roberts_c_009; 1/4"reel tape
  - John Day, 1965; roberts_c_008; 1/4"reel tape
  - John Hultberg, spring 1966; roberts_c_015; 1/4"reel tape
  - Kansas City Art Institute. Jose Guerrero, and Leo Manso, December 1964; 1965; roberts_c_013; 1/4"reel tape
  - Louise Nevelson: Meet The Artist, May 19, 1967; roberts_c_027; 1/4"reel tape
  - Man Ray, 1966; roberts_c_031; 1/4"reel tape
  - Marcel Duchamp, roberts_c_011; 1/4"reel tape
  - Nell Blaine, Will Barnet, May 1969; November 1969; roberts_c_002; 1/4"reel tape
  - Norman Narotzky, roberts_c_026; 1/4"reel tape
  - Ralph Rosenborg, N.Y.U., roberts_c_033; 1/4"reel tape
  - Reuben Tam and Leo Manso, December 1964; roberts_c_023; 1/4"reel tape
  - Richard Lindner part 1, spring 1965; roberts_c_020; 1/4"reel tape
  - Richard Lindner Part 2; broadcast WNYC, spring 1965; roberts_c_021; 1/4"reel tape
  - Riverside Radio Roundtable #50: "The Artist: Public Face, Private Face" with Colette Roberts, Charlotte Lichtblau, and Fielding Dawson. Cyril Peters moderates, January 1968; roberts_c_007; 1/4"reel tape
  - Robert Mallary; 465 Browne St. New Rochelle, NY., roberts_c_022; 1/4"reel tape
  - Robert Reid, fall 1968; roberts_c_032; 1/4"reel tape
  - Roy Lichtenstein Part 2, spring 1966; roberts_c_019; 1/4"reel tape
  - Roy Lichtenstein part one. Done by Lessei - a part missing, roberts_c_017; 1/4"reel tape
  - Roy Lichtenstein track 1 retake, spring 1966; roberts_c_018; 1/4"reel tape
  - Stanford Williams, roberts_c_037; 1/4"reel tape
  - Victor Candell: Meet the Artist Course, NYC, february 1969; roberts_c_003; 1/4"reel tape
  - Will Barnet: Meet the Artist, fall 1967; roberts_c_001; 1/4"reel tape
  - William Soles, roberts_c_034; 1/4"reel tape